<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC 
	"-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="en">
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Fedict eID Trust Service Administrator Manual</title>
		<copyright>
			<year>2008-2010</year>
			<holder>Fedict</holder>
		</copyright>
		<releaseinfo>16 Mar 2010</releaseinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Wim</firstname>
				<surname>Vandenhaute</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<abstract>
			<para>This manual serves as an entry point for setting up the eID
				Trust Service.</para>
		</abstract>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Installation</title>
		<para>
			The Fedict eID Trust Service comes with support for HSQL, MySQL
			and Oracle. This chapter explains how to initialize the database.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>HSQL</title>
			<para>
				If you wish to run the Fedict eID Trust Service using HSQL, you
				can
				use the JBoss distribution that comes with the Fedict eID Applet.
				Simply execute
				<code>mvn jboss:deploy</code>
				in the eid-trust-service-deploy artifact and you are good to go.
			</para>
			<para>
				Beware though, as parsing large CRL's might be memory
				intensive, you can quickly run into memory issues on HSQL. Therefore
				it is only recommended to use this during a test setup.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>MySQL</title>
			<para>
				If you wish to run the Fedict eID Trust Service using MySQL,
				you can
				use the eid-trust-service-mysql-distribution artifact.
				After
				unpacking you first have to initialize your database. To do so,
				execute following sql scripts which can be found in
				<code>./sql</code>
				.
				<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[
				mysql -u root -p < mysql-create-account.sql
				mysql -u trust -p < mysql-create-database.sql
				mysql -u trust -p trust < mysql-trust-service-ddl.sql
				]]></programlisting>
				. The default username/password for the
				<code>trust</code>
				database that is used by the Fedict eID Trust Service is
				<code>trust/trust</code>
				. If you wish to change this, you will have to manually modify the
				sql scripts and change the datasource in the jboss distribution. The
				latter can be found in
				<code>./jboss/server/default/deploy/trust-service-ds.xml</code>
				.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Oracle</title>
			<para>TBD</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Running</title>
		<para>
			After you have correctly setup your database, you can start the
			application by
			<code>./jboss/bin/run.sh -b 0.0.0.0</code>
			. Note that in case you choose HSQL as your database, you will have
			to first start the Fedict eID Applet JBoss distribution, followed by
			running the command
			<code>mvn jboss:deploy</code>
			from the eid-trust-service-deploy artifact. The MySQL and Oracle
			distribution have the Fedict eID Trust Service Application packaged
			and will be started automatically.
		</para>
		<para>
			After the application has started, it will have initialized itself
			with 3 default trust domains.
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					eID Authentication Trust Domain
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					eID Non Repudiation Trust Domain
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					eID National Registry Trust Domain
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			The default trust domain will be set to the eID Authentication
			Trust
			Domain. In order to function properly, the application needs to
			be
			able to make outgoing calls for CRL, OCSP, TSP and NTP. If you are
			running behind a proxy, you can setup the proxy using the
			administration webapp.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Administration</title>
		<para>
			The Fedict eID Trust Service comes with an administration
			portal. This portal allows you to setup your network proxy if any,
			manage trust domains and other aspects of the service.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Administrator registration</title>
			<para>
				To authenticate to the administrator portal, an eID
				authentication will be performed. If the service was freshly
				installed, the first successfull authentication will be
				automatically
				registered as administrator. Subsequent administrators
				will have to
				be accepted by this one. To do so you can, or perform a
				login which
				will add you as a pending administrator which can then be
				approved
				by
				an already approved administrator. Or a logged in
				administrator can
				directly add another administrator from within the
				admin portal
				after
				a successfull eID authentication.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Configuration</title>
			<section>
				<title>Network Configuration</title>
				<para>If you are operating behind a proxy, you can setup this in
					here and enable or disable the proxy configuration temporarily.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Clock Drift Detection</title>
				<para>
					The Fedict eID Trust Service comes with built in support for
					NTP and TSP.
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Information Message</title>
				<para>
					The Fedict eID Trust Service comes with a portal where regular
					users can perform a validation of their eID certificates. The
					information messages to be displayed on the initial page of that
					portal can be configured here. 
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>
	<appendix>
		<title>eID Trust Service Admin Manual License</title>
		<para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata format="PNG" fileref="cc.logo.large.png"
						scale="100" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			This document has been released under the Creative Commons license.
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata format="PNG" fileref="share.large.png" scale="20" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			You are free to Share — to copy, distribute and transmit the work.
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata format="PNG" fileref="by.large.png" scale="20" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			You must attribute the work in the manner specified by the author or
			licensor (but not in any way that suggests that they endorse you or
			your use of the work).
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata format="PNG" fileref="nc.large.png" scale="20" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			You may not use this work for commercial purposes.
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata format="PNG" fileref="nd.large.png" scale="20" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			You may not alter, transform, or build upon this work.
		</para>
		<para>
			More information about the Creative Commons license conditions can be
			found at
			<ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/">Creative Commons organization</ulink>
			.
		</para>
	</appendix>
	<appendix>
		<title>eID Trust Service License</title>
		<para>The eID Trust Service source code has been released under the
			GNU LGPL version 3.0.</para>
		<para>
			<code>This is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
				under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License version
				3.0
				as published by the Free Software Foundation.

				This software is
				distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
				but WITHOUT ANY
				WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
				MERCHANTABILITY or
				FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
				Lesser General Public
				License for more details.

				You should have received a copy of the GNU
				Lesser General Public
				License along with this software; if not, see
				http://www.gnu.org/licenses/.</code>
		</para>
	</appendix>
	<appendix>
		<title>Revision history</title>
		<table>
			<title>Revision history</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colwidth="1*" />
				<colspec colwidth="1*" />
				<colspec colwidth="2*" />
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Date</entry>
						<entry>Author</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>16 Mar 2010</entry>
						<entry>Wim Vandenhaute</entry>
						<entry>Initial version.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</appendix>
</article>